i didn't have in the notes that you get
for it
today's lecture seventeen dot org
apprehended and taken your
there is a few
for this to make a difference for you
guys are going to switch it up today
from
harp pipeline stuff in there
try and make a little bit
word review
some graphical stuff
i'm reading about the shall rarely
python classic but
hopefully make some pictures
so for those of you know we're gonna
thank you very fast but i think that
anyone expertise
what it what is a chart
the chart is a piece of paper but you
know the u dot ok were done today
let's go ahead and get started today
we're gonna
go over
q g_i_s_ which is a graphical g_i_s_
geographic information system
piece of software amber and also use
until called
and is it where it pissed off about
uh...
pronunciation
it's gta alle
and some people say brutal and some
people say to you know i'm and people to
think a lot
so today its
q g_i_s_ ra quant india
and
i call it you know
now is a reminder
in homework
to resubmitted your organelle file
becomes too
i'd like you today to submit your
org logfile today put on the server and
sent email me the mt five somehow fiore
logfile
and i think this is homework four
so you lose create a homework
flash zero
for directory and put in there
and just a million defied someone else
but you've already done that
company no
midterms
so remind you get the end of class if i
can remember
but just trying to get by
by midnight
few facilities before five a_m_ moments
ago finance
feel like it
just for fun
okay so let's talk about nautical charts
we're gonna use them as our sample data
said today
for two reasons one is we need a sample
is that the play with the tools of
learning learning
into understanding chart formats is kind
of important because you'll be probably
want to bring them in
throughout your work as background data
if you're not navigating or doing
anything
or you may be working on after critter
conducted so let's talk about the types
of charts
we've got and right now in the world
their support of
for a three types of charts
and they come in uh...
patrol here if you for your soldiers
r_n_c_
and he and see
this is
raster
nautical
charts
missus up picture this drawn up by
photographer as an actual image this is
the paper chart in white rock form
this is the d_n_c_ or electronic
navigation chart
an
and in the u_s_ now there may be other
formats off for the world but at least
areas
over here with our in sees
you have format called the f_b_
that is an image format incurable self
that's not really used for anything else
and over here we had two formats
one is called at fifty seven
and the other one is coming
slowly but surely through the stairs
bodies and it'll arrive here some decade
and that's that past one hundred
and these are that i think it's a great
show standards
for charts
this one
is
tonight he see standard will see the
text for a company a few format a little
bit
he comes from selling that
the spatial data transform
as d_t_s_
the format is really not terribly fun
this one is going to be based on
economic
life in all can be really awesome in
helpful it can also be
a big mass
hopefully the stairs group will work
really hard to make a very nice clean
design here about
we've yet to fully fee was coming out of
that
and for the for the two formats that
radio wave
days after the seven
and bs beads
animal also for your time and time for a
way
back in a turkey had to be a grades or
fags
i'm forcing
the version once we have contains igi
all the too old to read
bags from hoping that
in the next couple classes
i'm fine i think readout
new package for g although it installer
luxury bags
because right now and we can actually
read those
which is a big bummer because
secretive data from hyderabad surveys
that's really cool
i'd like you guys take a peek at
later in the class for ducking and look
at that could you know later
tear into sentences that to stick with
baghdad
mister
so let's start off with the electronic
charts
before jumping to that
the b_s_t_ format
is are cautionary warning
some of you later on your curtly and
upon standards committees and be
deciding before mappings
please don't pick a format owned by a
company
you do that
unit yourself in a world of pain
know any other idea office had managed
to pull out
a fast one
it's now okay to use b_s_t_ is but there
is a few years whenever one said
i've refused to write tools for this
format
and it got very on point
to try to stick with open standards when
you work on things because it's very
hard to you
build reliable software and not
yourself soon in the process
uh... when you're using formats that are
confused in close
let's take a peek at the no website
and i'll give you some opinions today
that are just my opinions they are not
now as of course he comes up for you in
ages opinions about
nautical charts and how you can akin to
use them
similar website if you search for ian
sees will take you to this and you're
gonna see a lot of
ours for registered trademarks
and a lot of warnings about stuff
in the notes you'll be able to straight
through this
but the click on the download noy m_c_s_
walked in walked serve
legal he is
and it's not clear
that somewhere in the middle there's an
actually a quick button to actually go
to the data
instead of hiding in there
so i've got wings of the gets right to
it
there's a whole idea of what's permitted
use
and if you're on the ship
if your inner soul its regulations
animal regulations like joel
the u_s_ coast guard stuff like that you
may have all circles but if you're in
here
working with the davises u_s_ government
data
and we can use and abuse it as we see
fit
if we're trying to write a check
and you need carriage requirement for
charts
you have to get the data directly from
our prove person
and there are getting really good checks
in that process
of talk a little about cutting it down
away with mt five songs and things like
that where you can actually validate
that data there aren't any validations
in their process things a little hard to
follow
in this class
we can use this data however we like so
if you want a refund part of it and use
it in one of your projects
with the u_s_ government data gulfport
so you're all on u_s_ soil from leaking
we can have fun with this chart here
so they have also a copy some of the
uh... entertaining texting here about
copying and
displaying
yean season we can pretty much say
whatever
so if you could superseded chart
downloader
we've now
gotten a little bit closer to our charts
but not there yet
so there's a
click here to download karo it right now
the nation charts
not there yet
in here
i thought to be fun to work with they
charge for a local area because you're
going to be doing projects for
some ideal probably
and possibly a master's or ph d thesis
in this area and having char background
it in your
material and your store things you can
use is pretty
pretty handy
so there is a nice a link dot here for
new hampshire
and h under a key in seized by state
this kind of nice is our new features an
ordinary for a couple years
you can click on new hampshire
and she did a year
but you don't get data
you get another
permitted you statement
saying that there are still not be bad
and that you are except all of the
liability for using this date at which
they actually can't enforcing liability
on you know i've been lied to your
already have
and way down here at the bottom this
little tiny okay
the kids you are way too it javascript
finney
factor data
but the nice part is if you click
battened down load it
once you
save it
you can always have
right-click in the download window
uh... firefox
copy download link
you know how the directly or else
without data
and it's okay for you to just give that
u r l someone else
uh... which is what i'm doing for you
guys
so if you wanna skip all of that stuff
if i could find it here
you're actually ok to run
this debbie get commander describe the
dating or all of those
went uh... like five or six steps to get
towards the data
there's a lot of c_y_a_ disagree term
covered door
will copy dot one q let's go ahead and
get started in playing some games
have gone into
i think last seventeen emina paste in
that debbie get command
and we're gonna see if we can cause no
and i think they're being attacked by
ccom
thank you hadn't download that d_n_c_
zip file
philip labels
a lot with cars
and compressed with
easy to u_n_ jeezy two files
go ahead and and
use this study get command here
to grab that they are or if you were in
the weblink in you
went through all this craziness in fall
on
you can do that
go ahead and rabat data
salty could not pay soon i received for
change as i remembered
ever going to go and learn how to use
those that tool thought about it is that
the typically
if you use to windows
he probably double click a zip file wins
that comes up if you bought it
you get this graphical interface and you
have to do everything by hand
we're able to scripted if we want to go
with him and say
unzipped
well actually we back up here have a
couple of things i want to show you were
the first one is
and the five some
if i were no and i'm not
i would provide with my files and mt
five film
and there's also another check some
called s_h_ a
as a number of different
f_h_a_ versions these are
government-approved
checked some functions
that if you calculate them
you can tell you have the same file as
me
and if i were no i i would say
in or if you have good church leadership
you better and the check some on them
and make sure your check some matches
what's on the telus site
trout and turned them on file and it
might not actually match or might be a d
and we don't have any version numbers on
here
so many of my little soap box and say
here know it'd be really great if u
versions your charts delivery files
so now that i've said that and i feel
better
there
whether one more checks some and then
we're going to play with the file so
asstt jr
animated tab
that shows either some of the different
s_h_ a_ algorithm that around
two fifty six is a commonly used one
them please if this is the number of
beds in the checks on the generated
and the more beds the better purpose
lower is to compute
so will do f_h_a_ eighty five six
some and then the file name so and h
union sees it
and if you notice here
the indy five some was this long
so that's fairly long
the s_ h_ a_ one is super long
scanning bigger and bigger
aniket every got over a phone somebody
you'd probably get it wrong
but the idea with the water number is
that
with big files they're doing these
calculations about some number to go
with the file the more numbers you have
the less likely they probably are to
collide with each other have the same
number
something you really don't want to have
his two different files that are really
different
then at the same checked some
an s_h_ a_ is even better than ninety
five in terms of having
not having the chance of these
collisions
and we'll see more of that throughout
the semester will play without a little
bit with bags and some of the matter
data
let's go ahead and take a look at that
uh... wonder might you guys since were
back in the show and we haven't been
here
too much in a while you can see man
unzipped
and that will give you
the manual page four
the arms of command
if you think you can fall asleep in
eastern reading
regardless of which is this week
this class of useful information about
it
what you often really want is the unzip
dash dash help is probably more along
the lines of something that you're going
to want
is is usually froze commands and give
you a quick summary
what we're looking for is
list files
team we're also looking for those of a
roasted actually running around
that there's not uppercase warning to
lower case one i'm not saying he's list
for mostly
sort of saying unzipped
dash l for list
really wise before you go and unzipped
something
orion tarik
look inside
and make sure there is in something
bazaar in crazy in there
otherwise you might spend the next hour
trying to pick apart from any dot
stuck all over your computer with we are
characters and whatnot sold two dash v
for verbose and an h
underscore d_n_c_'s dogs that
to go ahead and type that animal kondu
uh...
listing of what's in our zip file
so thin tell you
uh... so i don't know if i don't
underlying
how it was compressed
who are not for the difference between
life and size will just ignore that
the date that they were so far worse
so these files are from
ten twenty five supriya recent
and inside a zip file they have it
something like the mt five re
essentially they have a c or c thirty
two
there aren't very many members in here
so there's a much greater chance of a
c_r_ c thirty two
having the same number for two different
files
and that was soft all the file names
and the no stared for
packaging charges they always unpacked
into this p_n_c_ root directory
four that's two seven charts
so it looks
looks ok will go ahead nuns at that city
state and zip
an h
underscore even sees dot zip
press enter
any should now have a bunch of files on
this
so let's take a peek at those and show
you a couple commands
their new as we go through taking a look
ls dash l will see that there should be
d_n_c_ root directory
amra go ahead and c_b_n_ two million
series
and will do it now it's tough sell
so you should see
a whole bunch of directories
there is u_s_
stands for united states
to is our resolution
and i think five arrive to really close
up charts
few and one is like a big regional
charts
and then it starts
how letter code
for l_h_ for new hampshire
and then followed by a recent chart
numbers and i'm not sure if the and his
halen odiaum
okay while wall close up some time with
the comeback in the notes
they're not only four and we know what
goes on
coax yet there is a remains uh... what's
remain
i like to read the read me and kick the
kicked me
so this should hopefully get it through
something more than just more legalese
and back down to bottom
they've got a set of chart information
about what's in this
directory tree
legrand queue for quick if you forgot my
fatwa flip-flops
let's play with some values command
thirsty you for disk usage
just hit delete here
it's gonna list
probably in your k or half k
the number of
bytes image
each of these folders
remember that we can do an aged for
human readable
so that i will tell you that you point
six megabytes
four point three megabytes
i'm gonna show you our fun command
called find
which you do it fine if you say
find space and i'm starting directory
and after that you can tell it please
buy me certain kinds of files but if you
don't tell anything it'll find u every
file onto that path
which if you do that for life flash on
the computer the top root directory
it's gonna west every file on your
computer
and if it might take
happening
but we're going to hear inside of the
team c route which is not that they had
to go ahead and try it
and see every single file that in this
directory tree
what what you do as you can then passed
out to other commands and then they can
operate on such a files
there's a command called file if you
remember from before
so it's a file star
and i'll tell us
what types of files we have
and you can see that uh... the user
agreement from noah is in some
not ascii form
kinda funky
uh... but we can do is we can use that
fine commander path on the list of all
the files
to you
true file command
and then we can pass the final every
single thing in here so we can
if we didn't know what kind of far
better and ran into which is going to be
at fifty-seven
here's how we would ask
through the file
will delete vertical bar for the years
heights
there's a funky command called x args
which takes one-line out of the input
so each file estimate then passed out to
the program that we're gonna get it
so sizzle full weird still say x-large
file
press enter into negotiable name by name
find period pipe x args
so we want to run
this command
go ahead and hit enter you should see
text goes feeling bein
to tell you the file type of a thanks
for everything that's in here
and unfortunately when it comes to our
charts
it just says this is some sort of data
not very helpful
i've been trying to work with the
authors of
to ad in various charts types in things
like that and i haven't quite figured
out
the best string to give them to identify
at fifty seven or we're getting there
go ahead and get all the unique with the
file types if you remember
to got each file listed here
and then a colin so you can split these
up based on the coin
thing to remember that command in unix
to split on some character bubba type on
one that's good
at that point goods rumors play but
if we're not in python
anybody remember our units command that
might
split apart
based on a character
yes i heard i heard a cut
source they cut
the dash d options as what the woman
there were any use for any use the colon
to cut that
and then you can say dash after which
field
and remember pipe accounts from zero
lots of unix commands don't
so we wanted
take the second field so this would be
our
fuel number one in the anything after
that in the next group movie field of
the few so three dash f two
tried that press answer
forgive you second
you wanna run this command right here
so here we go
and that way the filings are
disappearing
werner try that again ever had collapsed
a into the unique set of entries
there's mobile ways to do this but this
is the way that i can you do i do have
sort
and i get the dash hw for unique flag so
that's a u
and what we should get back is a list
just of
the unique types that were in there
can see that
reversed putting this together is using
slightly different forms of taxed
something came back as an alias maya
image file which is clearly
misidentified since i don't think we
have any delete files in here
cd sql us not directory
you need to go into the d_n_c_ root
directory
cd into that directory
and then you should be
with those files
if you look at my pumped up there
this is research tools that you're going
to till the squash club seventeen slash
an indian theaters forwards
seemed to be in that same directory
well it isn't very interesting and this
case
we're working with more more datatypes
so remember these kinds of commands
to get yourself reorient
there's nothing like getting a big blob
of data from somebody and not knowing
what's in their what type of dating is
and this is a way to start out looking
at that so we're gonna see a number of
work on data today
so let's go ahead and we're gonna go
into a one of the new hampshire chart
so it's going to u_s_
and make it out here to get the list
there's an h
and we have zero one zero two i'm gonna
pick randomly
so now
u_p_s_ bt actual do a clear
i don't read as its who's coming with me
yet but if you
if your screen gets too crazy one in the
back at the top
type clear
it's just a thought
leader p abt
that was a clear
to do and i have a pure sleeve
sometimes there's been a screen was just
too much stuff if it's a little crazy
so let's take a look at what's in here
and we've got a bunch of text files the
talk about what's in here
this down here with the zero zero zero
is actually going to be
arcadia you need to do ls
and see what you've got in there
you control you clear that morning
now type ls and see what you've got
around
now if you look through here
you need to pick one of these so you're
looking for the one like this one right
here is the one i went into of and so we
need to go into that directly
so you're looking at my prompt
so we have is a couple times so i'm
gonna go back to list really quick
when you're looking at my prompt up here
this is my username
then so if you name act
this is the host name so alton for the
same for all of you guys universal
machine so this is the host name colin
this till that means by home directory
flash
class this is a directory
seventeen directory yes here it is a
directory flash and then this is the
director they were actually in right
here
dollar sign
in this case it is the prompt so is that
and add the information that tells you
about where you are
and then this is where i start typing
so when you see this if you want to know
where i'm at need that dollar fine out
of there
so that that was a little bit confusing
so if you put the dollar fine in and try
to get to where i'm at
you're going to have trouble if you
could that are fine
and remember that till the isn't
an actual pack alltel dot that's a
reference to your home directory
software that helps
and i'll do a quick
demonstration
so if we do from a copy this pettit copy
and taste and media control a jump back
to being in that one
and i do and echo if u memories echoed
try things out so this is the actual
power
of where i'm at
so hopefully that if you guys
begin back a little bit and
work on path skills important to be able
to have a sense of where at
what's going on
and always remember
youth p_m_a_b_c_ where you're at if it's
confusing
and allies to see what's in your
directory
so if you're trying to find something is
not coming up
those of the chief u_n_ z should use
along with the ako
to get yourself resorted
take a deep breath when you get confused
with unix
and try again start with those guys
if we do it
file star so on everything in there
we've got our
couple tax that all it's you guys read
on your own since it's not very exciting
halverson chart information these two
files
are our effort to seven chart so in here
each church starts off as doctor zero
zero zero
after
main file any other files and here that
are the same name with thought and then
any current list of numbers
those are chart updates when the program
reserve chart every set first file on
the list are supplying
all the files after it builds up the
chart dataset
and let's take a peek in there
it's useful
alwaz big advocate of people jumping in
and looking at the data even if you
don't understand it
there's actually a lot in there that
you'll start to pick up
if you just pray that you look at it
might be binary data
maybe means nothing
but give it a go
sold last
u_s_
five
go look at in our chart
and it's probably going to be kinda
gross
and that's a lot gross
but in here
what's going on and if you've read
through this
we start to learn to read through like
this is the fact random numbers they're
probably important but i don't know it
right here
i think so slash i_t_c_ eight two one
one
that's actually the standard
that's used to write a fifty-seven data
and that's how i figured out what format
has to be seven running with bells on
any of his a bunch of other stuff you
could probably figure out
a little bit about the chart
all we've got
if you're bored
we'll retrain you fools actually
understand this rather than having to
dig into too much
even if you didn't have any tools on
your computer
you can start to read up on what is this
format and what's in this file
so cute equipped
let's go ahead and use a tool that
actually knows about charts
so from that you know
we had to turn into the news today are
two groups
we have which you are
these are the bacteria
thing so i can lines and points
in color over if you want
business had a winds point shapes
polygons
all i thought you might drop at hand
and then
we have the actual g doll tools
so this is going to be your
and this is your rafter data worked for
image like data
so revealing radio rhapsody
seventy-year-old yard tools and we have
the first program here in the seat is
bilgi are info
beget enter he'll give us a little bit
of info
but we can see men fuji are
and you can read up on all the different
options that it's got
and the key one we want to see first
is dash dash formats
fit q
fuji are
info
dash dash formats
so this command
right there
pass at the lessons i think it's going
to give me a lot of stuff
self-pride
labs
and hit enter
and these are the format so that may be
familiar to you some of the may sound
like gibberish
if you know all of them you could have
my job happily
sit down there and you can teach you
about it but i don't know the mall
for example i have no idea but at the
end they is
but there's all kinds of musical files
you may have run into you may have heard
of it has reshaped final you might have
heard uh... at fifty seven
the few minutes ago
we have csd for comma-separated values
this is gpx is a format for g_p_s_ is
came down support from the war
jere jason
is a very heaney internet format
g_m_t_ i'm not sure which for refugee in
g_i_ is
anderson databases syndicates base
innocent
but there's quite a few format supported
by the storm
but it supports our effort to seven
chart so that means we don't need to
know the mechanics of how type
get in to rescue seven at the fights
so we can say
fuji are info
and our charts u_s_
presenter and hopefully it says
something
saying quite a bit right away that gives
you a warning that's pretty important
the driver in the software
doesn't support update which means that
there is there a one file isn't being
read
unabomber
and then it goes through a research
telling you about what's inside
and with a chart
if you think about the navigation chart
they have different layers the cover
different types of data
anybody know what i see end ta already
often
caution area
there's all sorts of different areas and
if you
if you've got to be a distt
if you're mariner
you probably know most of these
c_b_s_ is not a silly by that akram
bully locations there's bridges
there so i think there's all kinds of
really useful information in there
and we can start to grab some of it
however you cannot scripted
not in this window and only runs on
windows
so if you want to have an army of
process
running on the server you're going to
have a bit of a hard time with the
carrots one
it's not bad
you know one of the using it by hand
and at that place in great tools out
there
by all sorts of different vendors i
think has risk i think every year
terraces gotta get breeder high packed
lots of other companies will do that
but we're gonna go through the command
line style of things
busted two seven is going to be going
away
i think it'll take a decade or two
before his disappears
so let's try
converting this to couple different
formats
let's use the o_j_ yar to hu g or
command
you can do a dash age
for help i believe
i'll show you a quick command since it
it's kind of
overwhelming
but there are some quick easy commence
to do with
let's try making a came out
music and art
o_j_ yaar can you tell it the flat out
that you want with the dash f
so came out
this is world to get back with you see
your output file so u_s_
five
dot came out
and u_s_ five code zero zero zero for
input
and go ahead and answer on this
we're not going to hoping that people
are because it's not very good inside of
the virtual machine
but afterwards if u wanna put back in
like your drop box
you can lead to kim il american bring up
down the mac or windows
ornery one xbox and u_s_ to hit enter
it'll go off and create camo
i'd like to get a lot of visualizations
that need charts in the background it
needs if airways and for traffic lanes
this is a great way to spread them out
and put it in the background of your
data
so they can do a lots
star dot came out
which if you are female pop up
don't feel like you have to understand
this but then you can go and searching a
sense of all these things that are being
created in there for came out
and you'll see there's actually
here's some geometry
there's a polygon defining some object
inside of uh... chart
this case i think it's probably a bridge
helpful but not great
let's try it comma-separated values
we've worked without up again
go up to oral commands
rate change
came out the csd
and came out csd
and go ahead and answer on this
and you should see a whole lot of
warnings and complaints
the csd format doesn't have a lot of
support for geometry
it's not going to work too well the will
take a peek
you can give me airs
okay so what you do is you actually met
k mail
so he did he have changed both that
hamas yet
they should change the activity i
stepped and also the question on there's
two spots
civilian get their message you argue
both of those
the capital's right here do matter yes
here is your choice that you can make
that he was he same you'd like for a
year
and it will happily create something of
whatever name it
the great thing about extensions is
you can make them whenever you want
and it might screw things up pretty good
that's the thing that he can run the
file commando and might be a little tell
you that you're not looking at least i
you worry he's less
and you can you start seeing things like
a mailing your csd
is communal crazy so it's still in
dallas dot showing here to see what it
created
always good to go back to the basics
his knows that this is blue
and surprisingly effective csd file
rights
uh... there's a deal recur for directory
that's kinda on
yet you might need to do it became
offline about csd thing first
so we have a directory
let's go in there soto ncd until u_s_
five
plus years the number cabin
their auto complete
it often does what you doing so if you
have a cd appear
it's content we realize that you don't
care about anything else in the strict
rio grande
subdirectory
so cd into their
to halifax shell
and you should see a whole lot of junk
analyst take a look at one that might be
interesting
for a blizzard doing out figure of about
great day and you've got something out
there you might want to know
strong winds
one way to get that from the land area
right here is land area so maybe we can
try and use that one
sold to you
lasts
and then
tell andy tab
area time okay there we go
hit enter
and take a peek inside of that file
so hit enter and natural gas
i kid from a life of me seeing here
court if i can directly use
so i don't know what all of these things
mean yet i haven't looked them all up
i'm wondering if this could be include
accordance or it could be something else
you have to count
through here the number of commas and
look through and say
which one is it and i think it's
actually just a nineteen ember of some
sort
so it doesn't look like there's any good
cordoned thing here
t three
six seventy knowing
seven eight nine it's domain
so those are all empty and most of these
so not very helpful
basis and that is down there but they're
good
but we don't have coordinates
says kinda hard you spatial data without
ordnance
so this is the format is not something
that we really want
it was good idea but
so let's use
are g_i_s_ program q g_i_s_
guilty applications amarin that we've
been doing so much command-line and i
thought and whatnot let's go perfectly
program for a bit remember
duly means graphical user interface
as opposed to like sticky an old and
yucky
donor science
quantum g_i_s_
and start that up
and you'll see something public this
taking over your entire screen
i'm going to you
make that cover much of the screen
by clicking this right-hand mutton
thought one of you
we can have the layers
and you can build up whole max it's very
much like uh... park maps and things
like that
and we're gonna go ahead and try and
load up
our land area
so do you
abductor later
any should have a dialogue out
and the browse over here
will get you towards looking for the
dataset
i'm really
if anybody can just type in huge long
past correctly over time
impressed i guess you peaked in here
i'm typically using the browse when i do
this
and you'll need to navigate
to research tools and i'm gonna go to
class
class seventeen
d_n_c_ route because he is building up
the path up here
and we were in the u_s_ an h one
you can see some of the father treated
but we really want that original char
data
we need to hear press open
avoided a supplement to tell you guys
and i forgot sardonic secret down here
typically starts off white
have reshaped files
and you won't see anything else i'm not
sure why it does this look like this
i like to be off the all the files
summitry select of files
and then take your
over then more stuff will show up
services please visit rosier
yet actually using
thirty g acts as using gmail
too low that later
spent here this time and should say
something else like it would yaar
something or other
are you in
sulekha
at that time
and then all files at the very bottom
so you want to do pat victor later
and browse
then i weeded first go to a tab worth a
g_ r_ k_ n_ o_
and change that to all files
about
you needed to browse
quick open if you get to that point and
then you have a quick open again
and hope we'll see a map on your screen
yes right
many many steps
so i'm gonna click open
sore on the uh...
u_s_ five h zero one and dot zero zero
zero
it's now let me show you that
happen here's your data set you can
click open
it doesn't just open the entire chart it
once thought you pick which way you're
gonna look at
so we can scroll down
so land area
nineteen land area this tells us i think
that we've got like sixty seven
well geometry features in there and
click ok
and why does everybody have a different
color
into things i didn't notice
fun fun
lesson number one is you can pick
whatever color you want
so for me it's the chocolate for you
it's been a br click
on that land area layer
so very similar to illustrator or
jim or
a number of programs it does layers
anchor properties
and then since i don't
through on the land hot pink
i might make it karine
and then you click ok
many it's quick ok ken
and i have green lands
you picked from land
okay so that's loading up some geometry
let's also load up the police
point is pretty handy to use
say got measures on the field so will go
view
british at another vector lawyer
and i would have browse it's been a
remember where you were
so if you did all over the place your u
still gonna suffer trying to find things
but if you have browse
should take you right back to where you
are
so selective zero zero zero file again
parts of the chart quick open
and open again
and now let's pick who were down the
coast
pain from the bruins your wine
fired believe laps
so they know what the
fell eighty part of doing means
click ok
and i'm gonna make the screen bigger
because that'll help
that crash
architect took you guys real quick
we're doing that
there is a uh... an info button it's
like a little errol within our next to
it click that and try clicking on the
police
and i'll try to catch a few guys faster
layer opened
advocate where
prowess veeru
hoping
uh... you'd see me do it again
net www
we in the area
they and i have yet to recover
layer have actor where
brown
my zero zero zero
orphan
open phenomena pic five
without the should be cokie guys
and now i have
by ending the lease
so if you haven't done it yet
there lots of tools to help you out of
here
and one of them
he'd be
right here
identify features
and it changes your cursor in here
to be a little if i want
and you can click on the billy's
typically i_d_
and
get lots of information about the bully
that you're going to need to know if you
look up in the ass descendants and if
you want to know what
all these things are for
stays
he says yes
dept
uh...
hopefully
yeah
uh...
so that you were the air masses we saw
about not using the updated version
were not using the updated version
sort of using the zero zero zero portion
if you want to pay the author of acosta
at it
he will be happy to have it if
the the o_j_ art all i don't think it
knows how to read deserves or wonder
your two files
i think we're out of luck
until now a co-op sizzle features
together into a whole new char against
them
and there's update
sore kinda stuck
and the thing is it's open source code
so that
resources are
we can't complain about it we can pay
some of the fix it
or we can fix it ourselves
or we can just unfortunately with
practical support that will this limited
category
so it's not perfect
but you get this going and if you need
to chart update then you can either pick
errors tool
and tip echoing from but a lot of times
all you need is the basics
there are times to having the charges
just your background data is fantastic
you just knowing where
the waterways are where the police are
generally
is what's going on and then what you're
doing a sunday to go on top of that
and if you actually building a nautical
chart you're probably using
when the very expensive tools like
carrots to put together your chart
separatism impose you'll see various
buoys
out you can
zooming zoom out
with uh...
this guy's weakens using the
intersections
there's lots of other stuff that we can
do it this and hopefully will be getting
into more of it as we go throughout the
whole
semester
this tool can actually read obsolete
huge datasets
thank him for the men from big servers
and we can do
all kinds of things you stuff
a lot of which i haven't tried yet so
will be digging into his we go
and i think now's a good time to switch
over to you
plaster charts
will still have the s_p_
gonna hide this guy
him
if you want the f_-fifteen to view
we do it with we have some software he
received from the people bring this does
it
at fifty two is
hybrid nicely
a painful standard
to view visualizations with the
traditional chart you
and everybody i've talked to his written
and i think you can read a recovery that
the symbolically
there you pretty frustrated after doing
that
it's doable place not very funny thick
it's a very painful stands overplay
so in that case if you really need the
church arts and logy
you can try to import from someplace
you can go under properties and you can
start picking symbolically for things if
you've got some an icon set
but typically
char people don't use if this often
so isn't like you hear some of the first
charting thai people to really spend
time with key g_i_s_
so people tend to use a little bit
buddies at a time for other tasks
so it's not had a lot of exposure in the
chart world
writes let's go down and search for bsd
but getting a rash of charts or just
gone through
that louis loud and land area
andrew were common get navigation chart
so now we get to go back to you
the opposite coast survey website
and we're gonna get the new hampshire
set of charts
now with images there almost always
bigger than you or
in terms of filesize surrounding it
twenty seven megabytes
but if we go back to that
tiki max i've actually saved going for
you guys somewhere
wearing a crater sells all space to put
that in so i'm gonna go
cv
tell the flash class
seventeen
submitted cleared
so in the way to be search
control us senior team x window
to the click of here
and you can show us
anti d_s_p_
and then control a or something like
that or just go down there he's
and if you just click on like that
likely their at some point
now look at your right to the rest of
charts
so i'd like to get the link right to
know is that that we need
never youth
so if you look great down below
there's a big in source s_h_
amber and i got your getting
profiles with that you get
i'm going to be in class seventeen
an imminent grabbed this point
if you want to go through that chart
ppm
from a copy the debbie get
and be lazy
so we're gonna grab ads that we're gonna
skip all those warnings
sql promise not to navigate
thousand-foot ship off of what we do the
right
so that'll be under that getting a
russian navigation chart section
and then class seventeen
and we go ahead and do again
seems like a little bit longer being
twenty-seven megabytes
healthiest silver spring notices that
they get a whole lot of chart downloads
from succumb
to be get yet you're gonna want probably
move back up to the class seventeen
first
seeking to make a controlling
uh... yeah it alternative funds during
the second half pounds for a comment
mostly these commands you can against
that
shift his shift and not
so now go back to your cd concede you're
missing a slash until late in the class
there's an article on ap
that uses the rapture dot will charge
from now on
the application is in a written all that
well it doesn't cash or save any of the
charts locally
if you pay in around a three gets the
chart every time you come back to the
area
so someone spinning around like the
whole u_s_ east coast up the down a
couple times
that means they download all the charts
from noah like four or five times
chris two thousand nine
all of sudden no went all my goodness
third of our down off the charts are
from the iphone
as you can see
which had an application
a felony and on what platform never
liked while
i thought is super important to charting
well yet important
we had about aptitude kept telling
charts as fast as possible from allah
basically what i meant is that no need
to go find an offer and say can you
please put in cash is in your software
if you don't keep downloading or charts
all day long
those bastards doing that respects your
number of downloads is a dangerous
dangerous game
all right so we have it
we have a zip file
forever from before we can say unzip
dash held that he and others that file
to you
take a peek within their
r_n_c_ zip
services are unzip command the brett
hume
and in the notes that i also talk about
for this one to because i like that
beat a dead horse doing mt five psalms
an f_h_a_ two fifty six is
on the data if you come back and do
these notes again in a couple months
those numbers might change
meaning that no i outdated the child
without any really
wait tell from the files that they've
gone changed and other than the fact
that they did
sure its deep down in there
it's also an a catalog file
patella filed actually work
we get into but we don't have a
correctional yet
alfonse for the critique
this is why indy five sons are awesome
because then you
he starts going what's happening
okay sir
okay let's do an ally special at that
files p
will be my luck if they have to go to
work with
and then
and we've been dependent but somebody
important
and stephanie differ
let me try to make it
uh... if anyone else going in different
let's see what happens
will i get
news interesting
me quick double-check that meet into the
four mt five song
dropbox
house
would not be my luck it looks like noah
has out there that file between this
moving in now
going on for an update now right
so do you uh... huh
we'll go back up a moron
the unzip dash l dash he and hopefully
working here is the same thing that i
expected
and you should see a whole bunch of
files that safe dot bsd and dots kgp
and the funny part about bs bs is
decayed p files actually the b_s_t_ file
so that the actual image data is the
katie steve i want to call this the kpc
format
we have to live with it because it's its
old crusty and will be with us for a few
more years
so thought had nuns at that
cancer playing with some ratcheted up as
it is actually i liked the look
of russia charts they just look pretty
nice on the by mail or an lines all over
them that we don't use any more
within our country
fool do ans it ten h
r_n_c_
and it should say inflating inflating
inflating and we have a whole bunch of
file fam
we can run uh...
do u dash h
on r and h
par n c
if we do know is that cell which is
better to do first you'll see there's no
news
directory called bsd root
okay so
hit up here
this is a doing the same dash l dash he
is doing it so fast that the screen is
refreshing
that's clock ticking with unix is when
when you've got a machine is fast
any rerun the same commander beckham and
fully wrap the screen
it may actually
never look like the screening changed
senior commanders disappear he and you
prompt actually means you've run
every drew the whole screen
and he was too fast rewrite a catch
uh... so you go and take off the
national nasty predicament unzipped is
just on zip in the following
so you can do it to u dash h
and b_ if you were
and you'll see that there's a bunch of
directories
unfortunately
unlike dyess fifty seven's
i don't know how to interpret those
numbers in terms of which chart that is
without chart map in front of me
and i didn't bring one today
and she was one there's a lot of them
online but i'm not going to go looking
was gonna pick one or random
so we're gonna
skippy can do the same file commands
onto really quick through faith file
was going to be if you were in the
western and look at what's more stuff we
intended to so we see the into their
to find period
so finds dot tight
x arcs
file so i take each line
from the fine commandment opposite over
to file
them unless they cut
dash he cohen
desh f
to so effective field
it's going to have the name
and if i'm going to die for you
give it a go if you don't get go back to
the notes later on
ticket i'm typing out you'll see
committed we're doing exact same thing
as last time
and then sort dashiell
press center and hope that i take it
right
and what we'd get is
ascii text data directories
and more ascii text of a slightly
different form
so not very interesting
unfortunately file doesn't know much
about charts so we got to work on that
yet
ul especial will see our directory
cinnamon a look at which one i used
before
the cd thirteen
two seven four
or special
and we have
one
charts
but our chart of actually got five
images and it looks like
but katie's r_d_ image data
and the b_s_t_ is actually some added a
little with it
and we're gonna be brave
let's take a look at this bsd image is a
little bit different notes
so let's take a look at our the s_p_ so
what's
thirteen
two seven four dot bsd
now this one have a little less of the
like reversed
uh... collard
and hopefully it's a little more
readable
that's got these three-letter codes
and then some data after it
and if you look great here
c h t seems to be a coded tells us
well but the picture came
keeping into hampton harbor
side a lapsed
that sounds pretty good
so i think c h t s
probably the code printer canon
so let's try and use that real quick
this kind of at the time when you look
at a file format you realize you can
actually do a lot with something that
you don't know very much about
separates a cv
doc dot to go up one directly to our
viewers
and let's say
find
and they were in a state
hex ours
and that was seized usery
p_h_d_
in the notated differently i actually
did grep
c_h_ teen star slashed are not the s_p_
their similar
and terms of finding files
so hit enter
and that gives you
phil donahue and more answers
if you have a pile of charts sitting and
directory
it may be the whole u_s_ charts it may
not
you can go unused crap
to go find out which church you go out
sitting on the computer
sumbly that's a nice example of
mixing and matching commands in the bash
cell to start putting together
some knowledge about what you've got
you know for example
leading up right in your office
and somebody gives you
ten thousand charts from all over the
world
going to be no fun to go heartened
through for which you need you can start
learning how to run kit right commands
like this they will ban help you big
through all that data really quickly
trying to know
you can remember these numbers is not
very far
okay so let's go back in there
so cd
thirteen
two seven four
and certainly tight clear again
and let's go ahead and try to take a
peek at some of the state a
now we use
fuji are purbeck today dot
and you know it's for rapture data
so we're gonna use a command called t
doll info because they hope to have such
formats
and this has even more formats than the
o_j_ our side of things
sergio info dash dash formats
all the formats the distal knows how to
read
and there are some really crazy formats
in here
i don't know what they are
if you if you know if formats off if
you're probably uh...
pretty tired i've had it all that
usage ego info
and then
we can look at our charts i hit tab
and the first saw the files in here
and we have files one through
five of the types of member and hit
enter yet
will just pick the first one
so here's the commander in iran
press answer and g all spent trying tell
something about dot chart
some of its gonna make a lot of sense in
someone's going to make very little
signs
and there's a lot of jcp
picture here
so there's the commander in
it tells us that it's
reading of the s_p_ map tak
it tells us about the projection system
so there's all the projection for all of
this chart
peas are ground control points so that
the point or chart that no locations
thereafter cure pixel and i think so
take their place in the world and helps
you jewlery projections of toward either
and there's no
water-borne
and then tells you will have more
mandated on here
and then it's got some
corner information in terms of the
pixels
so we've now got a little bit of info
uh... b_s_t_
and i'll leave it up to you to go off
and read about the if these if you want
to know
but let's convert one of those two
picture rossi about charissa me care
around
and there's another g document called
udall translate
that we can make was just make it into a
p_n_g_
if that's not a geospatial format but we
could definitely go look at the picture
dash aleph is output format
would say p_n_g_
buffet one three
q seven former school born dot
kpm
the first
assoc first comes our input so this is
the
the b_s_t_ k p final
and then or help with so thirteen two
seven four
explore one dot p and g
amid double check that before it hit
enter
and the program's going to be a runoff
and it's going to make a picture for us
let's do that for couple them
sold it for two
cd replaced two different numbers
there's one right here
and that one right here with the field
press answer runs often does that
and three
so i think that work
now we can say display
startup p_n_g_
or reactions do you know a special first
so now we have a couple p_n_g_ images
running around in there
and we can use the image magic display
finance
to take a peek at them
so to display
startup p_n_g_
and press enter
philip and when they weren't here
so its display
star
period or for starting in june
so then you can use all pain window to
drag around
where you are in chart in get nauseous
looking at the screen
the just click you get image magic
window you can save you
capsize
half size and you can see now return
it doesn't do very good job of zooming
so it looks pretty
recruits spit
we always have a picture of our chart
we've seen it
in making its base through the next
turner believer
and then it works really hard for a bit
and many of the next chart
dancing around
space again before us a little bit
and what you can see is that one know
what chart
consists of a whole bunch of images
and hear the story to those little
mapping sets as a separate k p file
otherwise it is a real hard to work with
them because you have to have control
points deep inside of another picture
so here you can see the merrimack river
and then a queue to quit
right so let's try to in q g_i_s_
platforms yes down here
so if you bring up huge yes you can view
file
new project
and we're not gonna save what we did so
close without saving on our last one
and we can go back up to layers
and we did abductor lawyer before we're
not going to you that we're gonna go
down
ab roster layer
so raptors are basically pictures
and i'm gonna go back
it seems to keep track of rafters and
factors differently
and it keeps the old pop around so if
you have your actors and doctor
separated you'll remember that
may go into class
seventeen
and before we re in c route now we're
going to be espy route
and then thirteen two seven four
so you go in there
amber i picked one worldnews the first
one i guess
teens could not
and if you don't see anything
member click that bottom went down here
the it but you might say something like
you know
uh... it probably will default that's
unlike virtual raster
before leaving to you
suffered for a full raster good on the
bottom
pick haller finals
and then take that one
thirteen two seven four underscore one
dot k p
the computer worked really hard
and you have a chart
paperless by money used a zoom in
buttons you can see something
and you can and zoom in
tour region
he keeps coming
and you are now looking at chart
is north not up on that
this is the merrimack river i think it's
actually pretty close
in
for you thinkin workers
vichar shouldn't be repeated
or should be reviewed
accounts for the car one
i think is the coastline isn't directing
or south
it they try to get as much coastlines
awful to space to have on the paper
i haven't looked at that shilpi for
version of this
so you can also do you um
file new projects
close out saving
ab roster later
we can pick like number five
report
it was a cuppa north worth the north
point
north is actually out there
yet so happy birthday to the north out
okay by computers working hard on that
number five
america's so divert so much teens are
not so the fastest they don't have that
much ram for them so they might actually
have to work
pretty hard open a chart
pittsburgh
we should hang up here and we'll take a
look at bags
next time
on tuesday
and hopefully if i can pull together are
creating a g doll bill that actually can
read bags
because of the nice to be able actually
see the day and the vatican
because there's a
there some fun ones in this area we have
one of the white our file
and we have as some that have been the
tree
and we can take a peek at the medea and
see
i have the file from two thousand and
ten
and you can see if the file actually now
says the word wider and find it which it
didn't before
one of things that
to know about some these tools as that
if you're looking at parents
and your billing attorney fees are
always speaker exporting banks thicker
interface doesn't let you type in very
much
and so there's no way for the operator
to
create the complete correct meredith
file for our bag
from noah
so angie d_c_ has to go in use the same
tools that were using
to rewrite committed to the correct
after a gets to them
i guess